<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en" xml:lang="en">
<head>
 <title>Full transcript</title>
</head>
<body>
<h1>Full transcript</h1>
<pre>
>> Sean: Professor Brailsford - a lot of people
talk about von Neumann architecture and

we've talked about Babbage; we've talked
about Turing. Who was von Neumann ?!

>> DFB: We've done a lot about Turing; we've
done a fair bit about Babbage, in the

generation earlier. In fact a lot of
people, I guess, in the English-speaking

world would regard Turing, in some way, as
being the Father of Computing. He came up

with this very important result, in the
mid-thirties, about what was computable,

and as we now know. to his credit. he
wasn't at all afraid to burn himself with a

soldering iron and try to create
hardware. Which he did at Bletchley Park

during the war. So, yes, if he's the Father,
if Babbage was the Grandfather and if Ada,

Countess of Lovelace, was the Great-Aunt,

then who on earth was John von Neumann?
And why is he mentioned alongside Turing?

Well right at the outset let's say John
von Neumann was the impossibly talented,

impossibly charismatic, very wealthy,
Uncle to computing. It was he that, in the

mid-1940s, in a way, made it all happen by
the force of his own personality. And

kept it, not just in an enclosed
community, but encouraged all those who

wanted to build general-purpose
computers to come along to this Summer

School and do it.  But that really, I guess,
is in the future. It's where we've got to

get to in the von Neumann story. But, yes,
you're quite right Sean, to say that one

of the first phrases that almost any
computer scientist hears about is The

von Neumann Architecture for computers,
which to a large extent we still follow

even now - all of, what 60-70 years later. 
So, we've mentioned EDSAC before, we'll

be coming back to mention this very
important early computer again. But it is

a von Neumann machine and all it's
saying is [that] it's very simple to build a

computer. You need a Store, or Memory as
it's more commonly called nowadays, to

hold your instructions and your data.
You need a

control unit, often called a CPU now. And
you need an arithmetic capability - the

ALU, the arithmetic and logic unit. Again
many of you will know in modern chips

those two are often combined into what
we just call "the CPU chip" nowadays.

And you need input devices of various sorts
leading back to people's Teletypes [with] 

input/output devices for backup storage,
disk and so on. You need to be able to do

input and output. So there it is. It's
just one, two, three, four, five boxes - that

is the von Neumann architecture. And it's
very, very similar today. There was a big

debate at the time about that Store that
Memory. Shouldn't you, for safety's sake,

put the instructions of your program in
a different sort of memory to your data?

Wouldn't it be safer to do that and
better in some ways? On the other hand,

clearly, if you've got a good memory
technology, that works, the temptation

might be just to put them [instructions and data] 
in separate areas of that same technology and try

and take some sort of precaution about
them not interfering with each other. In

EDSAC the only way to get into a
subroutine and get back out of it again

was to over-write part of your program
instructions! Let's just return back to

this incredible character John von
Neumann. How does he fit in alongside

Alan Turing? Well, like I said, he's the
older, impossibly talented, Uncle. Did

Turing and von Neumann know each other?
Oh yes they did! They were both, basically,

trained as mathematicians. Von Neumann - 
it's hard to know where to begin and

where to end. You can't exaggerate enough 
about how

good he was. He was Hungarian and his
Hungarian name - where they give surnames

first - was, I think, Neumann Janos.
His father was very, very wealthy and

when one was quite young the family
became ennobled in Hungary. [They] became

basically at the level of Baron - 
hereditary Baron I think

over here. Janos was very talented; he was
a childhood prodigy. He could divide one

eight-digit number by another eight
digit-number in a fraction of a second

when he was aged about 6. He loved
history; he was a multi-talented polymath

he easily came top of the class he
effortlessly took in detail. And that's

the first thing that all of his
mathematics contemporaries said about

him was his sheer speed of picking up
new ideas and seeing the ramifications

of them. So he was notorious even as a
teenager, and as a maths undergrad. He did

his early education I think up to PhD
level in Budapest. He almost naturally

ended up at a place we mentioned before
in connection with Godel and Hilbert.

I'm talking, of course, about Gottingen
University in Germany. So Neumann Janos

makes the journey, via a PhD, to becoming
effectively the research assistant

to the superstar David Hilbert at
Gottingen. But because his family

had been ennobled he's not Janos Neumann 
any more - Neumann 

Janos sorry  - he's Johann von Neumann
- impossibly talented. Hilbert his

supervisor, at a seminar given by Johnny,

John,  Johann (!)  asked who his tailor was.
Because his impossibly smart

pinstripe suit was just a complete
knockout. So he was a legend almost the

moment he got there and did some
fabulously important work there. It was

obvious that for somebody of his talents
he was going to get a full Professorship

very quickly indeed. I think he became
impatient, waiting for it to happen at

any German university. So, in the late thirties 
- '37-'38?  Somewhere around there anyway -

Anyway he got an offer from Princeton, in
New Jersey. And that was, I don't know,

very timely. It all fitted in together
very well. As part of his tours of Europe,

giving seminars, and on his way to
Princeton, I think he met Turing in the

mid-thirties in Cambridge. Because he
gave seminars there

and I think a lot of mutual respect grew
up. I mean, obviously, Turing being in awe of

von Neumann wouldn't be so exceptional.
But after that 1936 paper of Turing's,

about decidability, following on from
Godel and all that, von Neumann rated

Turing - there was no question about that.
This was evidenced by the fact, you will

recall - those of you who have seen my previous
videos - that Turing also took a

sabbatical and worked with Alonzo Church at Princeton.

Well, von Neumann was there by that time.
Von Neumann was such a superstar, they not only

made him [full] Professor of Mathematics at
Princeton, at an absurdly early age - 

probably about 30, something like that.
But some of you will recall, right next

door to Princeton - about a mile and a
half across the meadows - is the Institute

for Advanced Study which had been
endowed in the early 1930s by a

multi-millionaire. And this really was
the ultimate Club to be invited to join.

You've got to be of the quality of
Einstein, who accepted the invitation.

Hermann Weyl one of the founders of
quantum mechanics; Godel - we know about

Godel. Godel was invited to just come
to IAS - Institute for Advanced Study at

Princeton - stay as long as you like. Yes,
you're a Professor; everything found: food

accommodation; the lot. All we want is to
have the greatest minds here. Von Neumann

was offered a professorship in that
community, I think at age 35 - maybe

slightly younger. Unbelievably young. He'd
hardly been at Princeton a year or two, as

an ordinary mathematics professor.
Everybody thought "This is a truly

phenomenal person". He reminded many
people of absolute superstars like

Newton, Gauss, Euler, Einstein, Hilbert
himself. Even at early to mid-

thirties they could see that potential
in him, there. So, yes, Turing visits

Princeton in 1938 - worked with Alonzo
Church - but also of course had frequent

interactions at seminars with von Neumann
And then came the big question,

if you recall, for Alan Turing: "Should I
return to England and do my patriotic

duty?" According to Andrew Hodges'
definitive biography of Turing,

Turing's father was all for Turing
staying in Princeton, you know: "Keep out

of the war; get a prestigious mathematics
job". And that was underlined by the fact

that von Neumann offered Turing a job. He
basically said: "Turing, would you like to

be my research assistant at the
Institute for Advanced Study?" Now

Turing could see, straight away, that would
just make you as a mathematician. 

You were invited, by the great von Neumann,
to be his research assistant, at IAS!

Only problem was, I think, first of all, I think
Alan Turing did feel a certain

patriotism in wanting to come home and
do his bit. There was also the worry that

at that time von Neumann had not
properly got into computing - he'd not

turned his considerable talents to
considering it - and for the research

assistantship he wanted Alan Turing to
do quantum mechanics, another of von

Neumann's great loves. And I don't think
Turing was keen on that because he

knew from experience, at Cambridge, where
he'd tried doing mathematical physics, it

really wasn't his arena at all. So he
politely declined with great thanks, came

back to England and the rest, if you like,
is more or less history. Now there's

"Johnny", as he'd now become. Johann von
Neumann speaker of four, five languages

including Italian and English, once he'd
transferred from Gottingen to Princeton,

wanted to become the all-American genius.
So he was ... on more formal occasions he

was just John von Neumann but to his
friends he was "Johnny". You can't 

exaggerate enough! I mean, his wife said: "He
can count everything but calories". He was

fond of food and drink; the champagne
parties! the glitz! the glamour! the

girlfriends! Good old Johnny - he
absolutely was the antithesis of the

shy mathematician. He was all-
encompassing and everybody who met him

was just stunned by how he could see 
his way through

problems in no time flat. And just do
impossible things. And so he was there, in

a very ,very nice position, Institute for
Advanced Study, even before the

Americans joined the war. But he stayed
there throughout the war. But being who

he was he was endlessly in demand to be
a consultant and, most famously, along

with people like J Robert Oppenheimer he
was one of the consultants employed on

the Manhattan Project - the atomic bomb and
the hydrogen bomb. But he was used by the

Army, the US Navy, the Air Force
- everybody wanted Johnny as their

consultant. And this even included, as the
war developed, the fact that one of the

earliest computers which we have
mentioned in a previous video was

University of Pennsylvania, Moore School
of Engineering. They helped develop the

ENIAC which, if you remember, was a vacuum
tube computer running on decimal

arithmetic and initially devoted to
gunnery trajectory calculations. It was a

bit late in 1946 to be in direct
strategic use in gunnery, Actually Johnny,

who by this time *of course* was a
consultant to the Moore School, devised a

way, I think, to turn ENIAC into being a
general purpose computer, although it

wasn't a very efficient one, and I
believe he used it for some calculations

relevant to the atomic bomb and all that
kind of thing. The natural question

arising with everybody at the end of the
war went like this: "We all know - or even

though it's top-secret at Bletchley Park
we have heard gentle rumours - that

computers are being developed all over
the place and you've always got to say:

Are they special-purpose? Are they
general-purpose? Are they

binary? Are they decimal? Are they fully
electronic? Or are they electromechanical?

And literally there must have been at
least a dozen machines around that

satisfied some of these criteria. If you
ask Germans about "Who's the father of

computing?", they'll  say "Konrad Zuse", He
developed electromechanical

machines that were Turing-complete and
calculated things. But they never got

beyond electromechanical. You get on to
electronic ones - you get Atanasoff 

and Berry's electronic, valve driven,
thing - special purpose though! Could solve

certain differential equations. And even
Tommy Flowers, and Colossus, we know,

special purpose: could decrypt Tunny traffic -
Lorenz cipher as it later become

known as. So, you've got everything
happening that if it's general-purpose

it's not yet electronic; if it's
special-purpose it is electronic but we

want it to be general-purpose. So, at the
end of the war was the perfect time to

get everybody together and say: "Look, now
that the war's over we all want to find

the way to do it correctly. To build
general-purpose, probably binary-based

because they're more reliable, all
electronic digital computers. How do we

do it"? And who better to lead the charge and

run a Summer School, and be associated
with it, than uncle Johnny of course!

And the Moore School at Pennsylvania, to their
great credit, did this. They decided that

the successor to ENIAC would be a thing
called EDVAC. They said, yeah, it's

going to take us three or four years to do
this but in the meantime here we are,

1946, why not all of you, all over the
world, who are interested in the quest to

build general-purpose, all electronic,
digital computers, probably based on the

binary system ... we'll hold a Summer School
in the Moore School of Engineering, 1946,

welcome everybody. Did Turing go to it?
He was, I believe, at that time at the

National Physical Laboratory in the UK
No he didn't.

Hated conferences did Turing. He wasn't
a clubbable character. He  couldn't stand

small-talk. Classic shy mathematician not 
at all like 

von Neumann, right? So Turing wasn't, if you
like, the UK representative there. And one

wonders whether he would also been held
back by Bletchley Park and the Official

Secrets Act because he'd only just left a
few years before. The representative from

the UK was somebody who was Turing's exact
contemporary. They had both done

mathematics in the early 1930s, at
Cambridge. They had both got first-class

degrees. Did they get on? Not very well!
But who's this other person? His name is

Maurice Wilkes - Maurice Vincent Wilkes - and
by the vagaries of job allocations

around about World War II, he didn't end
up at Bletchley Park, did Maurice, he ended

up in radar. But he knew enough about
mathematics and electronics to be in a

good position to do, or make, a von
Neumann machine in the UK in the period

from about 1946 onwards. But we'd better
stop there because Maurice and his EDSAC

is an extra story.
</pre>
</body>
</html>
